Finding Aid for Andrea Lael Cappaert Papers, 1952-1980
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Andrea Lael Cappaert Papers 1952-1980
Cappaert, Andrea Lael, 1952-1980.
3 linear ft..
8594 Aa 2
Ann Arbor, Michigan, poet and journal writer. Journals, manuscripts of poetry and short stories, photographs, scrapbooks and other materials documenting her struggles as a polio survivor to cope with her disability and to lead an independent life; papers concern in part her association with the youth culture of the 1960s and 1970s.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mr. and Mrs. LeRoy A. Cappaert (donor no. 3192 ) in March 1984. Additional materials were received.
The collection is open to research.
Andrea ("Andy") Lael Cappaert was born July 5, 1952 in Moline, Illinois, the daughter of Lael and LeRoy Cappaert. The following year, Andrea and her family moved to Ann Arbor, Michigan. At age two Andy was stricken with polio and for the rest of her life was confined to an iron lung at night and a portable respirator and wheelchair during the day. With the help and encouragement of her family and friends, however, Andy lived a full life. She traveled extensively and became an active participant in, and recorder off the youth culture of the 1960's and 1970's.
Andy attended Ann Arbor public schools and the University of Michigan. She worked at the Ozone House for several years and also at the Women's Book Store and the Center for Independent Living. In 1970, Andy moved out on her own. Andy died at the age of 27 on June 29, 1980.
The Andrea Cappaert papers date from 1952 to 1980 and measure 3 linear feet. The papers document Andy's involvement in the youth culture of the late 1960s and 1970s, and reflect her struggles as a handicapped woman to be an active participant in the world she lived in.
Subjects:
Alternative lifestyles.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1961-1970.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1971-1980.; Michigan--Social life and customs--20th century.; Poetry.; Poets, American--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Poliomyelitis--Patients--Michigan.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Conduct of life.; Women poets, American--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women with disabilities--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
African Americans.; Cappaert, Andrea Lael, 1952-1980.; Cappaert family.; Celebrations.; Clothing and dress--1971-1980.; Handicapped persons.; Hippies.; Motorcycles.; Music ensembles.; Persuasions (Musical group); Women.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Biographical
  Biographical material consists of a family history written by Andy; descriptions of the jobs she held from 1968-1979; scrapbooks compiled by her mother, Lael Cappaert, for the years, 1952-1969; and a book on the first nine years of Andy's life, And God Said No, written by her mother in 1961.
  - Cappaert Family History (Box 1)
  - Scrapbooks, 1952-1969, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - And God Said No by Lael Cappaert, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Work History, 1968-1979 (Box 1)
- Journals and Personal Papers, 1968-1979
  Journals and Personal Papers, 1968-1979, is the largest and most interesting series in the collection. Included are journals, arranged chronologically, from the time Andy was a junior in high school until 1979. The journals detail the events in her life and her emotions and feelings. As she grew older, Andy included correspondence and other personal papers in-her journals. At the end of the series are excerpts from her journals, including a large quantity of typed material.
  - September 1968-May 1974, 12 folders (Box 1)
  - June 1974-December 1977, 13 folders (Box 2)
  - January 1978-October 1979, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - Excerpts, from Journals, 1967-1979 (Box 3)
- Manuscripts of writings
  Manuscripts of Writings, 1970-1980, consists mainly of poetry and short stories that are largely autobiographical in content. Andy's drawings and illustrations are an interesting part of this series and are located in folders 6 and 7.
  - Poetry and Short Stories, 1970-1980, 7 folders (Box 3)
- The Rejects (A group of friends)
  Andy and her friends called themselves The Rejects. This series documents the activities and interests of the group.
  - Rejects Review, 1973-1980 (Box 3)
  - Writings about The Rejects, 1976 and 1979 (Box 3)
- Photographs
  - Personal, family, and rock group, "The Persuasions" (Box 3)